<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Letter to a friend concerning the partition treaty</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B25891</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12599516</idno>
  <idno type="VID">64125</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240962181</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1644A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16889</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12599516</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B25891)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64125)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 333:6a)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Letter to a friend concerning the partition treaty</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
                  <note>With: A second letter to a friend, concerning the partition treaty, with his answer. [London : s.n., 1700?]</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Spain --  History --  Charles II, 1665-1700.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  1689-1702.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Europe --  History --  1648-1715.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:64125:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64125:1"/>
            <head>A Letter to a Friend Concerning the Partition Treaty.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Return you many thanks for the trouble you have given your self, in let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting me know so regularly the Progress of affairs during this Session of Parliament, which (God be thanked for it,) is now come to an end; this was indeed much long'd for. I did not increase your trouble by putting you then to explain some things; which, at this distance were not well understood by us; but now that you are more at leisure, and that I know you have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitys of hearing matters as freely talk'd of, almost as they were at St. <hi>Stephen</hi>'s Chappel: I desire to know what indifferent Men and good Judges say of the Partition-Treaty. We in the Countrey do generally agree with our Representatives in condemning it. It seems strange to us, that our King, who was rais'd and advanc'd by his perpetual Opposition to the Court of <hi>France,</hi> who was provok'd not only to persist in it by all possible Indignities to his Person, and by their setting on so many Conspiracies against his Life, but by all the strongest Considerations both of Interest and Religion, could be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd on to treat with them, to trust them, and to procure them such an Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Empire</hi> as the Pertition Treaty gave them. It seems to us, that this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps may have driven the <hi>Spaniards</hi> to those desperate Coruses they have taken while they hop'd, by their late King's Will, to have kept their Monarchy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, tho' instead of saving the whole they have delivered it all over into the hands of the <hi>French,</hi> without a possibility of redemption, unless others take more care of them, then they have done of themselves. If I Judge of this matter wrong, I desire you will set me right. I am so much inclind not only to wish well, but to think well of the King that it raises in me a great uneasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to see a Cloud on any of his Actions and councills which gives them an ill appearance. I expect your answer to this, and without more Ceremony,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I am Yours, &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>NOW the scene of affairs is shifted and that I have nothing more to tell you from the two Houses, I refer you to the prints for the publick news, and so hop'd I might be respited for some time. But I see I am not yet quite at Liberty, you are putting me now on the hardest task in the World, to write of Politicks. It is an easie thing to tell you what this or t'other man said, even <hi>I—H— vs</hi> Speeches cost me only the Trouble of writing out what <hi>I</hi> remembred of them: Tho' the abusive strains in them came to thick that one drove out another: Only they were so oft repeated that what was lost at one time was recovered at another. But I am call'd on by you to treat of matters that I do not perfectly understand, nor can I arrive at a full informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on about them. You begin right at the Partition Treaty, which is said to have been the occasion of all the Miseries that we feel or fear. And since you will have me tell you my thoughts of it, I will doe it very freely. You know I am not apt to flatter or to think well of things because they are done by men of a high Character: My Biass lyes another way: There is so much occasion given for Censure, that common Observation make a man fall very naturally into a Disposition of thinking the worst, both of men and things.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:64125:2"/>
            <p>I have no excuse to make for our Courts trusting the <hi>French,</hi> or for their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring cordially into their Concerns. If I thought the King was capable either of loving or Trusting them, I could not maintain in my heart that affection and confidence which I ow'e him: It is impossible for me to believe it, he knows them too well, and has had too much practice in affairs to be guilty of such an Errour. As far as I understand the matter, this was the case. We and the <hi>Dutch</hi> had got thro' a great War at a vast Charge, and with infinite danger: We saw the weakness of <hi>Spain</hi> in the Buisness of <hi>Barcelona:</hi> There was no reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning on them as capable of making a stand if the King of <hi>France</hi> were freed from a War, since when that press'd him on all lands, yet with a small army he could at his Leisure take that important place: Had <hi>Spain</hi> any intrinsick strength to resist, there was time enough given them to have brought it all together. If I say <hi>France</hi> then with so small a body made such a conquest, what could be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from <hi>Spain</hi> when the <hi>French</hi> King should send his whole strength against them? <hi>A</hi> Fleet before <hi>Cadiz</hi> and two small Armies marching in thro <hi>Catalonia</hi> and <hi>Navarre</hi> might have found it hard to Subsist, but not to Conquer <hi>Spain.</hi> The <hi>Emperour</hi> abandoning all other Thoughts, had during the last War pursu'd his advantages against the <hi>Turks,</hi> and thereby had both exhausted his own strength, and disgusted his Allies. And on the Conclusion of the Peace of <hi>Reswick</hi> he had shew'd so great an Inclination to ruine <hi>Heresy</hi> at any Rate, and so little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the Honour of a Prince, to whom he ow'd so much, that this with some other things (that I love not to remember, because I hope that Court will grow Wiser) had given so just a Discontent, that few seem'd willing to engage in a New War for him and his Family. And his Councills were so dilatory and uncertain, that instead of pressing the Renewal of a General Alliance upon the Conclusion of the Peace, he seem'd not to regard it, when press'd thereto. We here were so weary of Taxes, and so jealous of a standing Army, that we broght down our Land Force, first to Twelve Thousand, and then to Seven. Our Fleet kept proportion to our Army. The <hi>Dutch</hi> did not disarm so fast, yet they had no force to spare, and to be sure, they would unwillingly engage in the Quarrel deeper than we did. While the debates concerning the Army were on foot, the ill Health of the K. of <hi>Spain</hi> was not forgot to be mention'd, and the Danger of the Progress that the <hi>French</hi> might make, if we were ruduc'd to such an Incapacity of protecting the <hi>Spainards,</hi> was often represented; but was often rejected with Indignation, as an Artifice of the Court to get an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my kept up. Things being in such a state, might not the King think that what was left for him to do, was to make the best Bargain he could. How bad soever the Partition may be, it seem'd still more desirable to yield up some parts of the <hi>Spainish</hi> Monarchy, than to let <hi>France</hi> conquer it, or rather take it all. <hi>Spain</hi> it self, the <hi>West-Indies</hi> and <hi>Flanders</hi> were the Branches of that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, in which we were chiefly concern'd, and while these were kept entire, in the same hands, our interests wery pretty safe. It is known, that what advantage soever the <hi>Spanish</hi> Grandees may make of the Dominions in and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Italy, Spain</hi> it self is not the stronger or richer for them, but much to the contrary. It is true, their interests at <hi>Rome</hi> are fortify'd by them, but we are little concern'd in those. It was not to be imagined, That <hi>France</hi> that had so much Noise with their pretensions to that Succession, and (how slight soever they may be) had involv'd all <hi>Europe</hi> in Wars upon yet slighter ones; and that saw how sure they were of Conquering so feeble an Enemy, and so weak a Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val, would let all this go for nothing. They did not fear a new Alliance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them, they knew well the Temper both of the <hi>English</hi> and <hi>Dutch.</hi> They therefore pretended to the <hi>Italian</hi> Dominions. If the King had been in Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to have talk'd roundly to them, certainly that had been both the wisest and the best method. But those who seem now the most inflam'd against the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition Treaty, know in their Consciences, that they themselves would never have engag'd in a new War, if the Dominions in <hi>Italy,</hi> much less if the <hi>Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy</hi> of <hi>Milan</hi> had been the only Point in debate. <hi>I</hi> leave it to you to judge what a Parliament would have said, if they had been call'd, and had found
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:64125:2"/> the <hi>French</hi> King in possession of perhaps all the <hi>Spanish</hi> Monarchy (as no doubt by what we have seen, he would soon have been, upon the Death of the K. of <hi>Spain</hi>) if they had discover'd, That Offers had been made to have compounded for that whole succession, by yielding up the Dominions in <hi>Italy,</hi> but that the King and his Ministers had rejected the Proposition: I doubt not, but then we should have had Impeachments upon Impeachments and the suspicions of selling and betraying the World into the hands of the <hi>French,</hi> would then have carryd such Characters of Probability, that we would, in reverse of S—<hi>B—S—'s</hi> subtil Discovery, have concluded who they were that were the Instruments of <hi>France,</hi> and suppos'd them to have been as well paid for it, as perhaps some have been for later Services. I confess the Dominions in <hi>Italy</hi> are very valuable, yet no Naval Power belonging to them, they are not now so consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable as they were some Years ago. Nor is it certain, that notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Partition Treaty, they would have been a sure Accession to the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> perhaps <hi>France</hi> would have found as much Opposition to it, as she is like to do now to her taking possession of the whole. The Pope would have struggled hard; It must have alarm'd the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> and indeed all Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mightily, to see the Pope surrounded with <hi>French</hi> Armies, and so much in their Power. The Popes pretensions on the Kingdom of <hi>Naples</hi> are of an old standing, and are not disputed. If the Pope should have refus'd to change his Vassal, and have upon that made use of the Arms of the Church, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited the <hi>Germans</hi> to his Assistance, and the <hi>Venetians</hi> to open Passages to them both by Sea and Land, this must have brought on a new War, and made <hi>Italy</hi> the seat of it. It would have made an irreconcilable Breach between <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Rome.</hi> It is easy to see, what this might have ended in. It is true, we by the Treaty were to have assisted the <hi>French,</hi> but in the Progress of the War, we might have found just Reasons of getting out of the Quarrel, and of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming the Umpires in it. Would it be a Reflection on the King's Honour, if it were suggested, That perhaps he would have stood to this Treaty as most Princes do, when they see where the advantage lyes, and as the <hi>French</hi> King has always done, and most signally in Relation to this very Treaty: <hi>I</hi> can't think so meanly of the King's Wisdom and Experience, as to believe that he built much on the Faith and Honour of his most Christian Majesty, but he might imagine that age had qualify'd that unquiet spirit, which has given the the World so much Disturbance. He might think that a bigotted Prince would above all other things desire to have the Papacy under his protection, that is to say at his Mercy. He would perhaps chuse rather to have the Dominions that were yielded to him by the Treaty, which he might expect without the Trouble and Charge of a War, than to embroil all his Affairs, and engage in the Decline of his Life in a War, of which it is not easy to see the End. A Lady that has great Credit with him, might be known to be fond of this Accession of Empire, both as laying a great Obligation on the Succession; and as securing the quiet and Life of one in whom she has so particular an Interest. A Ministry com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd of such young Persons as might hope to out-live their Monarch, for all his Immortality, would probably conclude that it would be more meritorious in another Reign to have extended the Empire of <hi>France,</hi> than to have rais'd a younger Son of <hi>France,</hi> so as perhaps he might be able one day to Dispute mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters with his Elder Brother. Upon one or more of those Reasons, or perhaps upon much better, the King might have reckon'd that the Treaty would have been better stood to by the <hi>French,</hi> without relying so entirely upon a Faith that had been so often given, and so seldom kept. He had likewise other things to depend on▪ It was reasonable to hope, that the <hi>Emperour</hi> would have come into it, tho' it had been only with this Design, that by his sons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in possession of the best parts of the <hi>Spanish</hi> Monarchy, he might thereby be the better enabled to lay Claim and struggle for the rest. Was it reason<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, to think that a Prince who had no Naval Force would have maintain'd a Dispute in oposition to all the Naval Power of the World united against him. And could a Prince of such an exhausted Revenue hope to succeed in Competi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64125:3"/> against a Court so dexterous in all the methods of it, and so well furnish'd with all that was necessary for making it most effectual. The <hi>Emperour's</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct in this matter had been so unaccountable in being so unactive to prevent it, that there was no Reason to suspect his not submitting to the Partition Treaty, when he saw it could not be help'd. The King might likewise trust somewhat to the Vertues and to the Vices of the <hi>Spaniards.</hi> They have had an antipathy to the <hi>French</hi> of above 200 Years standing. The <hi>Spaniards</hi> have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver before this time been guilty of betraying their Country, a Fidelitry with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out example has long supported a sinking Monarchy, and so it might have been still depended on, and their coming so tamely under a <hi>French</hi> Yoke, is a thing that was so little look'd for, that till all saw it, none could believe it. Upon all these Accounts it might seem reasonable enough for the King to imagin that the Treaty would have been stuck to without an Absolute Confidence in the Virtues of the most Christian King. And after all, as the K. of <hi>Spain</hi> had liv'd beyond all mens Expectations, so the King might have hop'd that he might lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish out yet a few years more, and then the Revenue of the Crown of <hi>England</hi> would have been clear'd of all Anticipations, and in the mean while the <hi>French</hi> King would have been Oblig'd to keep such Measures as would have secur'd us from all attempts, and have sunk the hopes of a Treacherous Party among our selves, who had set up their Rest upon the greatness of <hi>France,</hi> and begin now to revive their dead hopes, which seemd quite wither'd by the Peace of <hi>Reswick,</hi> and by the seeming Friendship between our Court and that of <hi>Versailes.</hi> And now, if you will lay all this together, you will retract a little of the forwardness, and of the Severity of the Censures with which you may be apt to load that Treaty. Every Partition-Treaty is not to be Condemn'd. The Triple Alliance was the Glory of K. <hi>Charles</hi>'s Reign, and would have been its strength, if he had stuck to it. And that was a Partition of the <hi>Spanish</hi> Nea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>herlands, of which the Council of <hi>Madrid</hi> complain'd so much, that they would abandon all <hi>Flanders,</hi> rather than submit to it; and yet they were wiser when they saw they could not help themselves. When <hi>Spain</hi> could not be defended but by our Arms, and by our Treasure, it might be both reasonable and just for us to consider what Interest we had in preserving any of their Dominions, and to take Care of those, wherein we were concern'd most nearly, and particularly, and best able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, but leave the rest to take their Fate. I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:64125:3"/>
            <head>A Second Letter to a Friend, concerning the Partition Treaty, with his Answer.</head>
            <p>I Am convinc'd, by your Letter, that it is not safe to rely on common Fame, or to yield too far to the impressions, which the first appearances of things, and some general pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices are apt to make. I consider the Partition Treaty after another manner than I did. I see, the King might have too good Reasons to hearken to a Proposal of that Nature, from the <hi>French</hi> King, without the least disposition to trust him, or to enter into close Measures with him; which in my Opinion must always prove fatal to himself, to his Kingdoms, and indeed to all the rest of <hi>Europe.</hi> But tho' you have gone a great way towards justifying the King, upon many personal accounts, for engaging in this Treaty; I do not find, you are your self reconcil'd to it. You rather make an Excuse for the King, than a Defence of the League. Therefore, for my own Satisfaction, and that of our Friends, I must become a little further troublesome to you. <hi>I</hi> can't but think it a lessening of the King's Character, if only in order to keep himself quiet at home, and to sink the Hopes of a Treacherors Party among our selves (as you express it,) he could be induc'd to enter into a Treaty unjust in it self and ruinous to Christendom. It is so Represented to us. One is said to have openly call'd it a Felonious Treaty. And we are told that a great man, in another Publick Assembly, said it was ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and dishonourable in the Project, and Mischievous in the Consequences. And yet after all, this Treaty was made by the King, let who will be concern'd in the Advice: And the <hi>Dutch</hi> are Parties to this Treaty, who are not us'd to be so grosly mistaken. We have been told, the King has a clear and more Universal Knowledg of the Affairs of <hi>Europe</hi> than any Man, and therbfore we are amaz'd to see him enter into an Affair so very lyable to censure. Tho you are no Friend to this Treaty, yet you hear the Talk of those who do not so much mislike it, and you will do me a very good Office, to make a report of what is said in favour of it, that I may know how they Vindicate the Kings Honour, which is very dear to me; and may not rest un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Suspicion that the King would engage in unwise and unjustifyable Measures, upon the bare Consideration of Personal Safety and Present Quiet.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I am, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOUR Enquiries are made with so honest a meaning, that a good Subject can hardly refuse what you desire. And yet methinks, you make but an odd Choice of one, whom you ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to be no Favourer of the Treaty of Partition, to represent to you what is said in its Justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. But I will obey you, as well as my memory will serve me, and what is omitted now may be supply'd in another Letter. It is not Flattery to say, the King is perfectly instructed in the Affairs of <hi>Europe.</hi> He has been at the head of Business for Thirty Years, and has encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred as great Difficulties as most Men ever did. This great experience, joyn'd with his thoughtful Temper and discerning Judgment, gives him advantages above most Princes, if not most men. This is truly my Opinion, and I should think my self happy, if I could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to confirm others in the same thoughts. My own Dread of the Power of <hi>France,</hi> and my Detestation of her Politicks, may possibly have form'd in me too unreasonable Prejudices against a Treaty, which seem'd to add so much to her Dominions, and may have occasion'd me not to give all the attention I ought, to the Arguments I have heard in defence of it; but I will fairly relate to you as much as I can call to mind of what I have heard on this Subject.</p>
            <p>The Objections to the Treaty of Partition go both to the Justice and to the Wisdom of it. It is said to be unjust in it self, as being a disposition of the Dominions of a Third Person then alive, made by a Codfederacy of two strangers, with one of the Pretenders to the Succession, without the Consent of the other. It is said also to be unjust, as being inconsistent with the separate Article of the Grand Alliance made 1689, whereby the States-General stipulate with the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, to assist him in taking the Succession of the <hi>Spanish Monarchy,</hi> in case of the then King of <hi>Spain's</hi> Death without Issue.</p>
            <p>It will not be amiss, for the better conceiving the Force of the Objections and the Answers, in a very few Words to state the several Pretensions to this great Succession. <hi>Philip</hi> the Third had Issue, besides his Son <hi>Philip</hi> the Fourth, Three Daughters; <hi>Anna,</hi> the Eldest, Marri'd to <hi>Lewis</hi> the Thirteenth, whose Son is the present <hi>French</hi> King; <hi>Margarita,</hi> the Second, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry'd to the Emperour <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the Third, Father of the present Emperour; and <hi>Catharina</hi> marry'd to <hi>Savoy: Philip</hi> the Fourth had Issue, besides the last King of <hi>Spain,</hi> dead without Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue, two Daughters; the Eldest <hi>Maria Theresa</hi> Marry'd to <hi>Lewis</hi> the Fourteenth who had Issue, the <hi>Dauphin;</hi> the other, <hi>Margarita,</hi> Marry'd to the present Emperour, and by him she had Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue, only <hi>Maria Antoinetta,</hi> first Wife to the Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and they had one Child, the late Electoral Prince, born in 1691, and who dy'd the Sixth of <hi>Februrary</hi> 1698.</p>
            <p>Upon the several Marriages of the Two Infantas with <hi>Lewis</hi> the Thirteenth and <hi>Lewis</hi> the Fourteenth, solemn Renounciations were made of all Claims to the Succession of the <hi>Spanish</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, by them or their descendants.</p>
            <p>Those Renounciations the House of <hi>Austria</hi> insists upon as valid, and so their Claim takes place. The <hi>French</hi> pretend to object to their Validity, and Claim the Succession, as if nothing had pass'd to bar them</p>
            <p>This being the Case, it appears, the first Treaty is not lyable to the Objection of want of proper Parties, for as the <hi>French</hi> King and the <hi>Dauphin</hi> entred into it; so the Elector of <hi>Bava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> in behalf of his Son, in whom, at that time, the whole Right of the House of <hi>Austria</hi> was indisputably lodg'd, was not only consenting, but promoted it.</p>
            <p>I should observe to you, that the Treaty of Partition is look'd upon as an abusive Name, by
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64125:4"/> those who think well of that Treaty. They say, it ought to be call'd, as it is, both in the Powers for making, and in the Treaty it self, a Treaty for the Preservation of the Peace of <hi>Europe.</hi> I should also observe to you, that this first Treaty had a very good Consequence, for assoon as the Transaction took Air, it not only occasion'd the King of <hi>Spain</hi> to make a Will, by which he declar'd the Electoral Prince, his universal Heir, but it made the Emperor to acquiesce in it, who till that time was vigorously soliciting, by his Minister at <hi>Madrid,</hi> for a Will in Favour of the Arch Duke.</p>
            <p>As to the second Treaty, it appears, by the Powers, which are in Print, That it began in <hi>Holland,</hi> by a Joynt-Negotiation of the Emperor's Plenipotentiary, with those of <hi>England, France,</hi> and the States-General; but the Emperour not thinking it fit to appear a Party in such a Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiation, for Reasons which were obvious enough, the Treaty was afterwards concluded without him.</p>
            <p>To say it was unjust for that Reason, is at the same time to say, the seperate Article of the Grand Alliance was unjust; for that was disposing of the Dominions of a King then living, by an agreement of two Strangers with one only of the Pretenders. As the Emperor was no Party to this last Treaty, so <hi>France</hi> was no Party to the first. If it was consistent with Justice, for the King of <hi>England</hi> and the States to agree, that one of the Pretenders should have the whole, without any Privity or Consent of the other, or of <hi>Spain:</hi> How could it be unjust (as to the Nature of the Contract) to enter into an Agreement with one only of the Pretenders, for distributing the Succession among all that claim'd.</p>
            <p>When Controversies arise between Sovereign Princes, there is no Judicature to determine of the Right. And they are at Liberty to refuse to submit to a Mediation, which is often hard to bring about, because both Parties must agree in the Mediators. Controversies of this sort would never have an End, but in the Ruine of one of the Parties, and perhaps of neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Nations in the Consequence, unless other Princes and States may by a proper interposition in such a manner as they think most agreeable to the Justice and to the Good of their own Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, oblige all the pretenders to recede from Extremities, and in Case of Obstinacy on any side, to assist those who are willing to yield, for the sake of Peace. This has been the approv'd Practice of all Ages. It is not necessary to mention Instances to prove what cannot be deny'd; — otherwise, what was done in the Case of the late Difference between <hi>Denmark</hi> and <hi>Holstein,</hi> is a fresh Example, much less is it necessary to go about to make a more particular application of this Rule to what was then the Case.</p>
            <p>A well-founded Apprehension of an unreasonable encrease of Power in a Neighbouring Prince, has been always held to be a just Ground of making War; it may be better defended, to be a just Reason to prevent it by a Treaty.</p>
            <p>An Accession of the entire <hi>Spanish</hi> Dominions, either to the Emperor (whose Claim was for himself, and his lineal Descendants) or to <hi>France,</hi> must unquestionably have form'd a Power extremely terrible to the rest of <hi>Europe.</hi> It was thereforefore necessary, to think of dividing the Succession, or turning it out of the direct Line, for the common Security of Christendom.</p>
            <p>Princes are bound to provide for the safety of their Subjects by all reasonable ways. If the most eligible cann't be arriv'd at, they must pursue such Methods as are practicable. It was visible the <hi>French</hi> King was resolv'd not to acquiesce in the Renunciations, his Flatterers had absolutely hardned him in the Opinion, that all those Solemn Acts were insignificant; and to make good these Sentiments, he had not only imployed his Lawyers, but his Arms, in the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, for many Yeaas. This the Emperor well knew, nay it is expresly declar'd in the sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Article of the Grand Alliance. So that when the Accident happen'd, the War was inevita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and the Accident was expected every day. No Care had been taken to form the necessary Alliances, on the conclusion of the Treaty of <hi>Reswick.</hi> Nothing was determin'd as to the <hi>Spainish</hi> Succession. No Provision for securing any thing Stipulated by the Grand Alliance. On the contrary, some things had pass'd at that time, which necessarily made a strangeness be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Emperor and the Protestant Princes. No Arguments were omitted to draw him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to New Measures, in order to make the Separate Article of the Grand alliance significant and effectual. And it was highly reasonable to insist upon Terms, when it was so fresh in memory, where the Burthen of the last War lay. But by reason of the very slow Measures of the Court of <hi>Vienna,</hi> and the particular interests which the Emperor thought himself under a necessity of mannaging with the Court at <hi>Madrid,</hi> nothing had been done or was likely to be done on that side, and at the same time the Subjects of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> seem'd neither willing nor well able to enter into a new War. <hi>France</hi> did not only continue arm'd, as during the War, but was at a vast Expence, in buying Horses for remounting their Cavalry, and for listing the ablest Men, as fast as they were disbanded by the Confederates. Without a Treaty a War was inevitable; or rather, <hi>France</hi> was Master of all without a War. This was the unhappy Necessity under which the King and the States found themselves, And in such Circumstances, where was the Injustice to accept of the Contract of the <hi>French</hi> King and the <hi>Dauphin,</hi> to content themselves with a part only of that vast Succession, and such a part as would not only be least in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenient to the Parties contracting, but to the General Liberty and security of <hi>Europe,</hi> rather than to leave him in Circumstances to seize the whole, or at least to take immediate Possession of those Parts, which would necessarily and suddenly endanger the Trade and Safety of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> and <hi>Dutch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon the foot of this treaty, the King and the States acquir'd an explicit and direct Right to compel the <hi>French</hi> King to acquiesce in the share allotted to him, which perhaps was want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before. For tho' <hi>Spain,</hi> in respect of the several Renunciations and solemn Acts, had an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press Right to oppose the future Pretences of <hi>France</hi> to any Part of that Succession, yet it was not plain, that by renewing his Claim, he violated any League with <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Holland,</hi> which would be the Case, after his entring into this Treaty.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:64125:4"/>
            <p>There is another very considerable thing to justify this Treaty, if it be true, (as it has been affirm'd,) that during the Transaction in <hi>Holland,</hi> in the Sumer 1699, the Emperor's Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster's, tho' they declar'd they could never make themselves Parties to an Agreement for dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring of the <hi>Spanish</hi> Monarchy, which would wholly ruine their affairs at <hi>Madrid,</hi> yet they did not express any great aversion to be seemingly forc'd to some Reasonable Terms. It has not often been known, that a deliberate Act of three Sovereign Powers, made upon very weighty Grounds, has been so frankly call'd <hi>unjust.</hi> The Emperour has not found cause to give it that hard Name. Nay, the <hi>French</hi> themselves who have violated this Treaty, in the most open and shameless Manner, and want to the highest Degree an Excuse for Breach of Faith, and had a good one, if the Treaty was unjust, yet they have never call'd it by that Name, but have contented themselves to take up the wretched Pretence, that by breaking the League, they have pursu'd the Spirit and meaning of it.</p>
            <p>This is all I shall say to you, at present, with respect to the <hi>Justice</hi> of this Treaty, that which you desire further, is to hear how it is defended from being Impolitick to such a Degree as to be Ridiculous, as you say it has been styl'd. I have already stated to you, how the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances of Affairs <hi>abroad</hi> stood, and in my Answer to your former Letter, I have observ'd to you what Disposition, as to <hi>War,</hi> had appear'd in <hi>England,</hi> and I will repeat nothing. It was evident, the <hi>French</hi> King was in a Condition to take possession of what Parts he pleas'd, of the <hi>Spanish</hi> Dominions, if not of all, without opposition: And that if some thing was hot done previously to the King of <hi>Spains</hi> Death, it would be too late then to talk of forming Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances.</p>
            <p>This Reasoning has been too unhappily justify'd by what we have seen since. <hi>France</hi> has ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Possession of all the Dominions of <hi>Spain,</hi> without the least Obstructions, and before any Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures could be entred upon to prevent it. The Friends to the Partition-Treaty say, the World will Judge which was the wisest Course, to provide before hand against so great an Evil, or to he put to play the difficult After-Game of recovering things out of the hands of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In so critical a Juncture, the King and the States-General judgd it reasonable, to hearken to the Proposal of a Negotiation, as the only means left to prevent the impending Destruction of <hi>Europe.</hi> They were not insensible, how little the <hi>French</hi> Faith was to be depended on, but they were not put in a worse Condition by the Treaty. On the contrary, if the <hi>French</hi> King should not stand to it, the <hi>English</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> had an indisputable Ground to resent the Perfidious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and would be justify'd by all <hi>Christendom,</hi> in directly joyning to assist the House of <hi>Austria.</hi> And till that Breach happen'd, the Empeaor might see how far he might depend upon their actual Assistance, and what care they had taken of the House of <hi>Austria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To think of Treating with the <hi>French</hi> King upon such a Subject, and to yield nothing to him, was indeed Ridiculous. All then that remain'd, was to make the best Terms possible; in the doing whereof, as the Interest of the House of <hi>Austria</hi> was to be sincerely and heartily espous'd, and a solicitous Care us'd that the Balance of <hi>Europe</hi> should not be entirely broken, so it concern'd <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> who were the Parties contracting, not to neglect themselves but to make such a Distribution, as might be least prejudicial to their Interests.</p>
            <p>The Three Things which they were principally oblig'd to take care of, was their security, their Trade, and the common interest of the Protestant Religion. In order to this, they were first to take care of the Barrier in <hi>Flanders,</hi> for making good whereof so much Money had been spent, and so much Blood had been spilt. It being demonstrably plain, that if <hi>France</hi> was pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sess'd of the <hi>Spanish Neitherlands,</hi> it was not possible for the <hi>Dutch</hi> to bear long the Expence of supporting themselves; and when they fell a Prey to <hi>France,</hi> (notwithstanding the vain dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses, we heard not long before, of what we were able to do,) <hi>England</hi> was not likely to be free any great while.</p>
            <p>The Second thing which concern'd both Nations highly, was the preserving the Trade of <hi>Spain,</hi> and the use of her Ports. This need not be inlarg'd upon, the present Apprehension of the Danger of losing this Advantage, has made it very sensibly understood by every body.</p>
            <p>The Third Thing which concern'd <hi>England</hi> infinitely, and The <hi>Dutch</hi> not a little, was to keep The <hi>West-Indies,</hi> and the Trade thither, in the Condition they then stood. For it will not be deny'd, if ever <hi>France</hi> can appropriate to it self the Trade of <hi>Spain,</hi> and The Management of the <hi>Spanish West-Indies,</hi> she will soon be Mistress of the World.</p>
            <p>These were the great Things to be first look'd after, and for these the Treaty did fully pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide. It is not to be deny'd but that the <hi>Turky</hi> Trade was of great consequence to both Nations, and the Trade of <hi>Italy</hi> not inconsiderable, especially to <hi>Holland;</hi> and it were to have been wish'd that every thing could have been entirely gain'd, but when that was impossible, the most weight was to be laid on what was of the greatest Consequence. It is said in a certain Letter, which is charg'd by some, as favouring the Partition-Treaty; and by others as written against it, That if <hi>Sicily</hi> were in the <hi>French</hi> hands, they would be entirely Masters of the <hi>Levant</hi> Trade. They who declare themselves for that Treaty, quarrel at that Expression as too forcible. No Question, in Case of a Rupture, if the <hi>French</hi> had <hi>Sicily,</hi> they might at least for a time, give a great Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption to the <hi>Turky</hi> Trade, but if the Ports of <hi>Spain</hi> and its Dominions were open to the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>English</hi> Fleets, that Inconvenience would be in a great Measure avoided. Whereas, as the Case now stands, for want of the Effect of such a Treaty, the <hi>Spanish</hi> Ports are like to be entirely shut up; and consequently all Trade into the <hi>Mediterranean,</hi> if ever a War should break out, must be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come entitely impracticable.</p>
            <p>The Treaty of Partition, if it had been stood to, had plac'd <hi>Spain,</hi> the <hi>West-Indies,</hi> the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> and <hi>Milan,</hi> in such hands, as <hi>France</hi> could expect no sincere Assistance from. What real Addition of Power <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Sicily</hi> would have brought to her, is not so plain, <hi>France</hi> is a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64125:5"/> compact united Strength. Whether she would have been stronger by the Possession of two re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Countries, whose Natives have the utmost hatred to the <hi>French,</hi> Experience only would have shewn. <hi>Italy</hi> would have been alarum'd to the last degree, to find the <hi>French</hi> taking Possession of so large a Part of it, which it could not be possible to prevent, considering the Power and Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>France.</hi> But this would not have been the first time that the <hi>French</hi> had got to be Masters of <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Sicily,</hi> and yet were not able to hold them. Certain it is the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> would have found it self oblig'd to set all its Engines on work to prevent the establishing of that Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, which was inevitably coming upon them. They would be discerning enough to see, that from the hour the <hi>French</hi> King became peaceably settled in the Possession of <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Sicily,</hi> the Pope must sink in his Character, and would be no more than a <hi>French</hi> Bishop. The rest of the Catholick World would hardly consider him as a Common Father, who could be made and unmade at the Pleasure of <hi>France.</hi> Without pretending to Prophecy, one may say literally, That Heaven and Earth would have been mov'd upon this Occasion: The Church would have drawn out all her Forces Spiritual and Temporal, and besides the Influence she would always have upon the <hi>Italian</hi> Princes and States, which is avowedly not little, They themselves are quick-sighted enough to see what different Figures the Princes of <hi>France</hi> make in this Age from what they made heretofore, and to learn Caution from so significant Examples. Besides, the Pope's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrances would have had the more Authority as well as Vigor from the scandalous Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance it would have had to the whole Papal World, that <hi>France</hi> in Conjunction with two Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Powers should dispose of the Fiefs of the Church. The Emperour would undoubtedly have been solicited by all sorts of Arguments to assist the Church, and assert the Liberty of <hi>Italy,</hi> and how far he might have been able to resist, might not be difficult to guess. All the Catholick Princes of <hi>Germany</hi> were at liberty to act as the Conjuncture invited them. The <hi>Italians</hi> would not have apprehended any thing from <hi>Spain,</hi> they would have understood easily which way the Arch-dukes Wishes would go. The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi>'s affection to the House of <hi>Austria</hi> is so well known, that it is certain the <hi>French</hi> could have depended on nothing from <hi>Milan,</hi> in his hands. And tho' the late Chancellor in his Letter, said, that if the Treaty should take place, and <hi>Milan</hi> could not be reliev'd by Sea, it would be of little signification in the hand of any Prince: We see he was mistaken, and that very powerful Reliefs might be sent by Land to <hi>Milan,</hi> and the Emperour and Empire might always have an open way into <hi>Italy,</hi> thro' that Countrey. The King of <hi>France</hi> would have been cautious to have left his Frontier naked towards <hi>Flanders,</hi> when in Possession of a Prince of the House of <hi>Austria,</hi> or to have left the <hi>Rhine</hi> unguarded, when the Pope would be sure to have a prevailing Power with the Ecclesiastical Electors, and the other Catholick Princes of the Empire.</p>
            <p>This would have been the highest Security to the Protestant Interest, for which certainly we were above all other things concern'd. <hi>Italy</hi> would have been the Scene of the War, where upon all Accounts we ought to wish it, and not only as being the most remote from us. The Apprehension of a Catholick League, which is no Chimaera, and which it is to be too justly fear'd may be the immediate Consequence of a settled Peace among the Popish Powers, when the Zeal of the Emperour, as well as of the <hi>French</hi> King is consider d, would have been far re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd. In such a State of Things, we could apprehend nothing as to our Trade, not even in the <hi>Mediterranean.</hi> All Parties would have found it reasonable to be courting the Great Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val Powers of the World. We might be Neuter if we thought fit, or might have made our own Terms. We were not bound to take any other Share in the War than we pleas'd, for tho' we stood oblig d to see the Treaty executed, yet in the utmost Strictness that was all. We were not bound to maintain the respective Parties in Possession. We might have enjoy'd the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of Peace, or we might have otherwise found our Advantages in return for our Assistance, in case we chose to give it to either side.</p>
            <p>But they who have a mind to extoll the Wisdom of the King and the States, for entring into the Treaty of Partition, found themselves most on the ill Consequences which have appear'd upon the laying it aside. They pretend to think it wonderful, that Men should be quarrelling with so much heat at a Transaction, whereby such large Territories of the King of <hi>Spain</hi>'s Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions were to be deliver'd up to the <hi>French</hi> King; and at the same time, with so much Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Temper see him take Possession of the <hi>WHOLE,</hi> and shew so little Concern to redeem that Time which was lost, by their late Coming Together. They say it will cost many Lives and much Treasure, before <hi>Europe</hi> can see Things upon so good a Foot, as that Treaty put them.</p>
            <p>They go further, and say, That the same Men, who promoted the Clamour at this Partition-Treaty, are labouring at this very time to make one much worse for <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> for the Liberty of <hi>Europe,</hi> and for the Protestant Interest. For already they stick not, in their Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses, to make it a Fault, to talk of asserting the Pretence of the House of <hi>Austria</hi> to the whole <hi>Spanish</hi> Succession, and this is not to be wonder'd at by any who observ'd their early Zeal for the Duke of <hi>Anjou</hi>'s being own'd as King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and their Question ready form'd for the Purpose.</p>
            <p>I have set down what occurr'd to my Memory, according to your desire. You must look on me as not responsible for the Solidity of any of these Arguments, on the one side; or pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to have said all that is to be said in Defence of the Treaty, on the other. I am so sen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>le of this latter, that I find my self under an Obligation of telling you, That upon your in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to me, what parts of the Account I have given you, appear to you to be most weak and imperfect, I will let you know, whether the Defect proceeded only from my want of Memory.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>I am,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:64125:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>